<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some observations on the late dangerous petition presented to the House of Commons, September 11. 1648.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W691C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E464_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E464_19*</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203707</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863559</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863559</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162242</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97106)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162242)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 74:E464[19], 74:E464[19*])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some observations on the late dangerous petition presented to the House of Commons, September 11. 1648.</title>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to William Walwyn. Not included in McMichael and Taft, The writings of William Walwyn.</note>
                  <note>A reprinting of and reply to a petition included within: To the right honourable, and supreame authority of this nation, the Commons in Parliament assembled.</note>
                  <note>"To the right honourable, and supreame authority of this nation, the Commons in Parliament assembled" = Thomason E.464[19*].</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy E.464[19]: "Sept ye 19"; annotation on Thomason copy E.464[19*]: "7ber 19th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>To the right honourable, and supreame authority of this nation, the Commons in Parliament assembled.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162242:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME OBSERVATIONS ON THE Late dangerous Petition preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Houſe of COMMONS, <hi>September</hi> 11. 1648.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROV. 22. 28.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>Remove not the ancient Land-markes</hi> or bounds, <hi>which thy fathers have ſet.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>PROV. 24. 21.</bibl>
               <p> 
                  <hi>My Son, feare thou the Lord, and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the Yeare 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:162242:2"/>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:162242:2"/>
            <head>Some Obſervations on the late dangerous Petition preſented to Houſe of Commons <hi>September</hi> 11. 1648.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow ſpecious ſoever this Petition may ſeeme to ſome, as whatever pretends removall of grievances is catching, yet upon a ſecond view, you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a continued vein of dangerous ſophiſtrie wrapt up in Equivocall tearmes from the beginning to the end: ſo that to undeceive well-mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people, it would require a more ſad animadverſion, then my preſent leiſure, or indeed abilities can afford you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that will hinder a Serpents entrance, muſt mainly take heed to the inſinuations of the head, which once admitted, ſteales in the whole body; Wherefore I will begin at the title, and unravel the whole piece, and in ſo doing, I doubt not to evince all, that when theſe Petitioners tongues are ſmootheſt, their mindes are rougheſt, when they give faireſt language, their intentions are ſowleſt, ſondly deſigning with <hi>Mercury</hi> in the fable to pipe out <hi>Argus</hi> his eyes, and imitate thoſe theeves, who rob with muſicke.</p>
            <p>But withdraw the Curtaine now. <hi>To the right Honourable and Supream authority of this Nation the Commons in Parliament aſſembled The humble Petition,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sheweth That no Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is more juſt in the Conſtitution then that of Parliaments.</hi> Joyn
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:162242:3"/> theſe together and ſpell them, you that pretend ſo great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the conſtitution of an Engliſh Parliament: did you never heare of <hi>we the Lords and Commons,</hi> &amp;c. If you thinke the conſtitution of Parliament juſt, doe you thinke the conjunction of both houſes unjuſt? Who are you that take upon you to legitimate one of theſe twins, and baſtardize the other? Are you ignorant how they have been born and bred together? This was the old plot, <hi>Divide &amp; Impera.</hi> The court aime, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the two Houſes; they knew well enough the fall of the one, would be the evening of the others ruine, that the firſt could not be ſtifled, but the ſecond would be ſtrangled. Will you put a new cape upon an old cloake, and build upon a Malignant foundation? Sure ſome new light hath diſcovered unto theſe men, how to make a body ſubſiſt all of belly, for tryall whereof they are whetting apace to cut off our Parliament at the waſt; This is the reaſon why the Ordinances are ſtiled Illegall in the <hi>Warning-piece,</hi> becauſe the Lords have a hand therein: The Peers are the skreene which ſtands between Prerogative and Liberty, and keeps each from ſcorching other; That <hi>Commiſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra cervicis</hi> which marries the head to the body; The mean be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the extreames, A Gallery between Royalty and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty which makes them keep their due diſtance; They are le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitives, which allay Monarchy, and of <hi>Mercury</hi> ſublimate make it a wholeſome medicine: In ſum by their means we are famed and envyed, for our happy <hi>mixed Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as the end of all Government is the ſafety and freedome of the Governed,</hi> &amp;c. What doe you quote the end of Government to the Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iament? for did they ever abridge juſt freedome? but what ever you talke of freedome, you mean licentiouſneſſe as is evident as well by the whole tenour of this <hi>Ochlocraticall</hi> Petition, as by the <hi>report of that warning-piece (but charged with murdering ſhot)</hi> which is but the <hi>conſtruing Booke</hi> of this, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by its complaint of the ſtop of this very Petition, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeditious pamphlets, in the laſt page. Now what great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is there between tyrannicall and licentious Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Are not both Arbitrary? The one pleaſeth not good men, the other diſpleaſeth wiſe men: The one can eaſily doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162242:3"/> the other can hardly doe good: in that the inſolent have too much ſway, in this the fooliſh, yet is there more hope in Tyranny, for be there one or two evill Princes like droughts of immoderate raines, and rivers overflowing their bankes, a good ſucceſſour like a fit of ſeaſonable weather may repaire the others breaches and render us our own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with Intereſt: but in an Anarchy what can be expected, but a never dying ſucceſſion of confuſion? There is a lively analogy between the populacy and the Sea, Both uphold only light things, let the heavy ſinke, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the horrible ingratitude to their braveſt Captaines and beſt deſerving Citizens of the Roman and Athenian people. However the Sea may ſometimes deceive the eye, with the ſmoothneſſe of its glaſſy ſurface, yet we know it alwaies lyable to ſtorms &amp; tempeſts &amp; that as inconſtant as the Planet whoſe influence moves it, it hath ſuddenly wrapped it ſelf up in ſurd billowes and devoured whom even now it ſmiled upon: Thus the unbridled multitude when at the calmeſt want but their flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Oratours to blow up their waves till they tumble and gather, then foame by mutuall attrition then roare and rage till the maſt crackes under the ſayles, the rudder deceives the hand of the Pilot, and anon the whole Ship of the Common-wealth ſplit againſt the rockes of their inconſiderateneſſe. Every head of this Hydra is another <hi>Eolus</hi> who makes uſe of the popular windes <hi>viz.</hi> their affections, to reach the haven of his private aimes, and then ſhift for your ſelves. Of this tribe ſeemes to me the <hi>primum mobile</hi> of this Petition, whom I vehemently ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be ſome <hi>Licinius</hi> or <hi>Sextius</hi> that gapes for the firſt fruits of a Plebeian Conſulate. <hi>And to make it the moſt abſolute and free nation of the world.</hi> I am here extreamely puzled how to tye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the end of Goevrnment and abſolute liberty into one knot nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all my tugging can I make the ones end reach the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers beginning for what need Government where every man according to their principles may be his own Governour, or do they mean their Governours ſhould be like glaſſe eys in a blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans head for faſhion not uſe? Tell us in plain tearms what you mean by <hi>moſt abſolute and free:</hi> If you mean an unreſtraint in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, tis every true, Patriots wiſh that piety and vertue may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162242:4"/> be the onely wayes to honour in this nation and that hereafter good men may reap ſome other recompenſe beſides the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their owne well doings: but if your ſence of abſolute freedome ſtretch to an unlimited freewill to doe what ever ſhall ſeeme right in your eyes, to act your owne dreames where a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d when you pleaſe without feare of controule, in contempt of authority, all which you daily practiſe; If this be the, Butt you ſhoot at, give me leave to invert your maxime, and tell you, that the end of all Government is indeed the ſafety of the Governed, in curbing that licentious and abſolute freedome here aimed at, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in reſtraining that <hi>Liberum arbitrium,</hi> in conceipt whereof all fleſh is ſo prone to ſwell. But this is the common ſin of Prince and People who caught with the ſame fallacy, wherewith the Divell foyled our firſt Parents and not content with the ſafe freedome of knowing and doing good, are ſtill fancying an additionall perfection till they are juſtly left <hi>miſerably free</hi> to bewayle the loſſe of their originall power, and fall from their primitive eſtate of freedome.</p>
            <p>Next <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ollowes a Catalogue of their grievances; They begin with the houſe of Lords (though not vouchſafed that title viz. of a houſe) whoſe juſt convening of Delinquents before them, they compare to the former ſupercilious proceedings of the Conncell board: but how juſtly we ſhall ſee, by examining the argument. Some Court Lords who moved but by the wire of their maſters paſſions did amiſſe; therefore no more Lords are to be truſted: Divers particular Noblemen uſurped an illegall authority over their inferiours, ſome out of arrogance, others onely by imitation; therefore the houſe of Peeres now acting as a court of Judicature according to the known lawes, is <hi>repugnant and deſtructive to the Commons juſt liberty,</hi> how does this comparriſon hold.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>And therefore in the firſt place you will be exceeding carefull to preſerve your juſt authority, from all prejudices of a negative voice in any perſon or perſons whatſoever</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and that you will not be induced to lay by your ſtrength, till you have ſatisfyed your underſtandings, in the undoubted ſecurity of your ſelves, and thoſe who have voluntarily and faithfully adhered to you,</hi> &amp;c. Here you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:162242:4"/> tell the Houſe of Commons in plaine termes, the Lords are but cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, which added indeed to their figure encreaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſumm, but of themſelves make no number, whence learnt you this Parliamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Arithmetick? Since when came an Ordiance to bee of no more force then an Order? this is to tell <hi>the Supreme authority of this Nation,</hi> that they underſtand not themſelves, nor their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, when they deſire, to any thing, the Lords concurrence: You'l alter your tone ſhortly, and tell the Houſe of Commons too, they ſhall be <hi>Supreme</hi> no longer then they pleaſe you. Doth not the ſame ſpirit of wild-fire, which here breathes upon the Nobility drive e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually againſt Lords and Commons in the <hi>Warning-piece?</hi> Where <hi>their Councels are termed deſtructive, their Votes, votes for Norman bondage, their Ordinances Illegall, where the</hi> Whole body of the City is rayled againſt and no other terme beſtowed, then <hi>Proud Malignant, Illegal Major of</hi> London, <hi>and his like brethren the Aldermen, and a few illegall Common-Councell men.</hi> Who ſees not by your inſolent carriage, that your venome is againſt all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Orders? while you may be permitted to ſpit your poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in ſecret, and to hatch young Cockatrices in your myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſeminaries, you p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t on a v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zard of zeale to the Houſe, and are ſure to hoyſe up title enough; (enough to drowne them, if they ſet ſayle therewith) but upon the leaſt alarum againſt your party, they ſhall be no more the Supreame authority of this Nation. <hi>But the vile of the Houſe and their Confederates, a company of Traytors to God and their Country, for thus are they already ſtiled in the Warning-piece;</hi> Nay, King, Parliament, Prieſt and People are there inveighed againſt. I wonder whence theſe are, who are comprehended under none of thoſe. Shortly wee ſhall have ſome of theſe ſeditious Tribunes ſtep up, and preferre <hi>Agra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ias leges:</hi> Is it not againſt the Common<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> priviledges to ſuffer any encloſure? Why ſhould any Patrician poſſeſſe more land then a Plebeian? hath not the one as much of <hi>Adams</hi> bloud in his veines as the other? The truth is, they feare the State of <hi>Licinius,</hi> condemn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by his owne Law <hi>De quingentis jugeris poſſidendis,</hi> and therefore aime at nothing leſſe then an equality, or extenſion of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons priviledges. How pregnant is hiſtories of examples of ſuch as alwayes pretended the eaſe of the Beaſt, till themſelves got into
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:162242:5"/> the ſaddle, and then who rode harder then they? who ever tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized more then theſe kind people, who now weare the pleas of Liberty and Conſcience threedbare, where they have enjoyed but an inch of Government? Let all Hiſtories ancient and moderne ſpeake. Let none of my Country-men therefore bee kindled by theſe Jack-ſtrawes, who will in concluſion burne themſelves, and thoſe who are ſet on fire by them. Learne to know, that in a well ordered Common-wealth, there is nothing more unequall then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality; let not the hands ſtraine to ſubmit the head to the feets trampling, leſt the necke of the body be thereby broken. You know what became of the diviſions betweene <hi>Abimelech</hi> and the men of <hi>Sichem;</hi> if you opinionatly perſecute the houſe of <hi>Abimelech,</hi> a fire may iſſue thence, when you little dreame thereof and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume you. Pray what got <hi>Athens</hi> by the Fines, impriſonments, baniſhments of their Nobility? Even as much as <hi>Rome</hi> by their Agrarian lawes, and other encroachments of the Tribunes upon the Patrician priviledges, which fits of convulſion extinguiſht that flouriſhing Common-wealth. During the War between the Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentines and <hi>Millaneſi, an dom.</hi> 1427. The popular faction at <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> having abated the inſolence of the Granders, by ſubjecting their moveables, and other goods to proportionable taxes, began now to ſwell, and not content with preſent redreſſe of grievances, fell to ripping up old ſores, and demanded ſatisfaction of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility for all unequall levies paſt: Indignation whereat had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned (ſaith my Author) the conjunction of the Nobility and Gentry with the common Enemy, (as upon the like occaſion they had formerly called in the Duke of <hi>Athens)</hi> had not <hi>Iohn de Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci</hi> timeouſly ſtopt the flux of theſe peccant humours, remonſtrating the folly of fretting at old wounds, when they ought rather to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent new; and if their uſage had formerly been unjuſt, they ought to thanke God, who had ſhewed the way to make it juſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelves with a middle-ſized victory: For he frequently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does who over-does. 'Twas an ancient <hi>arcanum, Non in omnia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licta, nec in ſingulos Authoresinquirere.</hi> Who ever deſires a Map of our Engliſh chaos, let him turne to the Florentine Hiſtory, where he ſhall find the mutuall obſtinate perſecutions of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ever barking at the preſent government, to have ſtrangled
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:162242:5"/> that Common-wealth, and introduced a Tyranny, under which they yet groane; <hi>His ego gratiora dictus alta eſſe ſcio: ſed me vera progratis loqui etſi meum ingenium non moveret, neceſſitas cogit, Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom equidem vobis placere, Quirites, ſed multo malo vos ſalvos eſſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This devolving ſo much upon the people cauſeth a double evill. 1. Honors are heaped upon ſuch as having never taſted therof, reliſh them the leſſe, and have leſſe occaſion (going without them) to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain. 2 They are taken away from ſuch, as having been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed thereto, will never reſt till they be reſtored; as the Sea af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſtorme never leaves tumbling and toſſing till his waves are le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled. Thus the injury on the one part, out weighs the benefit on the other, and for few friends, you make many enemies, who will alwayes be more ready to hurt, then thoſe to help you; Since men are naturally more prone to revenge of injuries, then recompenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of benefits, this ſeeming to import dammage and loſſe, the other profit and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>In the other branch of this Article, you deſire the Parliament not to disband, before they have well provided for their owne ſafety, and their adherents. All their Adherents, that I know, would be glad to ſee Armies disbanded places diſgarriſon'd and the poore waſted Countries in ſome meaſure eaſed; as ſoon as the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall judge it ſafe, whoſe very being induced thereunto is ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument enough to their modeſt friends of its ſafety. But who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces them to deveſt their ſtrength? any thing ſave reaſon? what ſawcineſſe is this to charge Supreme Authority, with ſo ſupreme weakneſſe, as that they are apt to be induced to things againſt their own underſtandings? They know their greateſt ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ength lies in the peoples hearts, and out of meere returnes of love have intertained a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ender care of their disburdning, as far as wiſedom will dictate. But who told you they were voring downe the Army? Nay you knew the contrary, by their late Votes for a new eſtabliſhment under Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> unleſſe you interpret the voting of ſome Troopes for <hi>Ireland</hi> a disbanding; however it bee, the Votes were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready paſſed long before this baſtard Petition was borne, and which renders your impudence inexcuſable, in your magiſterial de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of undoing what you knew was already done. But you love o walk in clouds, and may you at length emb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace a cloud in ſtead
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:162242:6"/> of your ambition'd <hi>Juno,</hi> ſhall be my prayer: In plaine Engliſh you are loth to ſee this Army by ſub-diviſions enfeebled, upon whoſe ſtrength you rely for ſupport wherein you thinke are many props of your extravagancy: you fancie to your ſelves wings out of their feathers, and therefore unwillingly ſee any quill dropt; fondlings, you dreame! The bulk of the Army are otherwiſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed; The ſounder part begin to ſmell your rottenneſſe; I know not by what misfortune, you have not ſo cloſe girt your <hi>Lamb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kins</hi> of late, but that you, <hi>Fox linings</hi> have appeared.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>That you will take off all Sentences, Fines and Impriſonments, impoſed on Commons by any whomſoever, without due courſe of Law, or judgement of their equalls and to give due reparations to all thoſe who have been ſo injuriouſh d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alt withall, and for preventing the like for time to come that you will enact all ſuch arbitrary proceedings to be capitall crimes.</hi> Here is a fine ſpun net to catch the ſimple: but what g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eater enemy to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uth then likehhood? If you underſtand by <hi>due,</hi> har ordinary <hi>courſe of law</hi> what Malignant could ſpeake higher language, or find, fitter engine wherewith to batter down what ever the Parliament hath been rearing up theſe five yeares? The ſafety of the governed, the end of government (to ſpeake in your own dialect) hath occaſioned the doing of many things above the ordinary courſe of law: ſtrange diſeaſes, unknown to <hi>Gallen</hi> and <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> have forced our State Phyſitians to new wayes of cure. If ſhame forbids you now the owning this conſtruction, all the ſenſe I can ſqueeze of this expreſſion, is a charge upon the Parliament for their commitment of ſome of your mutinous rabble, for which yet you would be loth to ſtand to the due courſe of law. Dare you talke of the due courſe of Law, which you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to overthrow in divers Articles of this very Petition? The complaint were juſter, that the Lawes are no more duly executed upon ſuch troublers of our Iſrael. So when you demand repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, you muſt unfold the riddle, for verily to us poore Ignorants you ſpeake in parables. I thinke you intend not Delinquents com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions be reſtored, although its poſſible, to get ſome of their hands to your Petition you may have gratified them in this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. For whom elſe hath the Parliament fined, ſentenced, or impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned? O, its true, I had forgot <hi>Rabſhakeh Lilbourne,</hi> whoſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:162242:6"/> merit at leaſt Letters of recommendation, to his name-ſake, <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> K. of <hi>Munſter,</hi> for the office of Grand Maſter of his Ordnance.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>That you permit no authority,</hi> &amp;c.) Agai ne, ſo fierce for lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity? long may be in this good humour I But I am afraid you will ſhake hands with it at the next turning. In the meane time let's examine whence cometh this zeal againſt an Oath <hi>ex Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio;</hi> is it not becauſe they abhorre the very name of <hi>duty?</hi> will you allow never a graine more to the Parliament then Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber? Muſt what this aſſumes for the preſent be unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ablebecauſe the other uſed it? ſundry emergenciesdaily happen which eſcape the foreſight of the moſt provident Lawgivers, who therefore have in every State, betruſted ſome with a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, whereby the ſupreame Magiſtracy is impowred to provide in caſes extra legall for the Common wealths indemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. The rule indeed uſually holds <hi>Nemo tenetur ſeipſum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere</hi> but if the State judge it expedient for the di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>covery of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Jeſuit, or Jeſuiticall—ſhall not the <hi>Publick</hi> Obtain that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour which the Law allowes in caſe of <hi>Private intereſt?</hi> A cleare conſcience fears not the touch ſtone, and whoever <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> ſtarts from the triall is therein <hi>nocent</hi> becauſe contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Onely ſuch owles as you, dread diſcovery and fly the day, therefore, whatever you may boaſt of your <hi>new lights</hi> they are at beſt but <hi>candle lights.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>That all ſtatvtes, Oathes and Covenants may be repealed</hi> &amp;c. What an ambuſh of <hi>Banditi</hi> is here broken out againſt the poor Statutes? Did not I tell you what would become of your pleas for legality? My Gentlemen are already skipt from the Law, to a falſe Goſpel: but no wonder they ſnarle here at mens Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes when they bark in the next at Gods Ordinances What a bitter pill is this ſame Covenant? Theſe Oſtriches who ſo eaſily ſwallow iron (they ſwoon at the noiſe of disbanding cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the Covenant: oh this lies hard at their heart for why? it is a <hi>Shibboleth</hi> whereby the mutionus <hi>Ephramites</hi> are diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; I commend <hi>Vulcans</hi> ingenuity out of whoſe forge came the <hi>warning piece</hi> who although he halt villanouſly in other matters, yet tells you like an honeſt rogue the <hi>Covenant is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:162242:7"/> becauſe it diſtinguiſhes <hi>the vile of the houſe from the faithfull of the houſe</hi> what unparalleld malapertneſſe is this to demand the abrogation of our lawes, the nullity of our ſolemne vowes as far forth as they may be <hi>conſtrued</hi> to their moleſtation? By whom ſhall they be conſtrued? by you? we are like then to have pretty endleſſe worke: for you know you are not bound to believe to morrow, what you make us believe you doe to day, ſo that ſhould we modell our lawes to your preſent liking, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we had done you may have ſprung a new opinion, or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>tender-hooft Sect</hi> may ariſe and taske us anew; May not Prieſts turne Independents, and with equall reaſon Petition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance? But you are <hi>peaceable and well-affected:</hi> I wiſh you may prove ſo, if you have helped us hitherto we ſee in this Petition by what hopes you were led, and that in the work you were wel affected only to your ſelves. For ſuppoſe a complyance with all your fanatick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, which yet is impoſſible, you draw ſo unevenly among your ſelves, would not your peaceable maximes ſuddenly ſet the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome on fire with war, ſpirituall war, debates, heart-burnings, envies, ſtrifes, contention? Read the hiſtories of your fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, and tremble at their examples: Who pleaded more peace then the German Anabaptiſts, till they got the reines of government into their hands, and then what divels incarnate ever acted ſuch villanies? O ſhun their foot-ſteps who ſo deſires to tread in the paths of life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thoſe Dutch Sectaries firſt, to make way for their innovations, that no regard of Conſcience or fidelity ſworne to the Magiſtrate might ſtop their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings broached this doctrine, that all Oaths in the time of the new Teſtament were unlawfull, and that therefore taken, or to be taken, they were of no validity. Ours only ſlice them as yet, and deſire their qualification: when they have obtained this, they will have ſomething elſe ready to obtrude upon us; for he that thinks they will ever be content, is to learn the nature of a Sectary: In the tayle of this Article lies this venemous clauſe, <hi>That none may be diſturbed for difference of opinion or practice in Religion:</hi> A worthy grievance! that every Enthuſiaſt ſhould not have his allowed Teraphim! nay, they are not content to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:162242:7"/> as they liſt, nor to practiſe what they liſt, unleſſe they have Letters of Mart to take up Proſelytes. All they can catch muſt be lawfull prize, and therefore they aske.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That no man for preaching or publiſhing his opinion in Religion in a peaceable way may be puniſhed or perſecuted as hereticall by Judges that are not infallible, but may be miſtaken as well as other men in their judgements, leaſt upon pretence of ſuppreſſing errours Sects or Schiſmes, the moſt neceſſary truths and ſincere profeſſours therof may be ſuppreſſed, as upon the like pretence it hath been in all ages.</hi> Mark how the Serpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t creeps, and every where leaves a filthy ſhine behind him; Hitherto they never pretended more then a tolleration, now they will have a patent under the broad Seale for publike vent of their falſe wayes, While they only uſed the buckler and weapons of defence, we pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yed and connived at their weakenes, ſuppoſing that nothing but a certaine habit of private aſſemblings forced upon conſcientious people by Prelaticall tyranny without any other obſtinacy, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinnued their withdrawings from publike worſhip: But now that they furbiſh the ſword and whet their teeth like ſharp arrowes, blow the trumpet with that man of Belial, <hi>Every man to his tents O Iſrael.</hi> It is high time to rub our eies and watch their progreſſe. Had they contained themſelves within their deſires and ſtuck to their <hi>Penates</hi> they might ſtill have pleaded the <hi>eaſe of weake breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren:</hi> But that al markets ſhould be open to their putid errours plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhews they never intended them other then for ſale and I appeale to all underſtanding Chriſtians, and ſuch as cheriſh the practiſe of piety and power of godlines, whether this be not a ſtraine beyond the tedder of a tender conſcience! Did not the Divell by theſe ſame inſtruments o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtruct the growing re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ormation in <hi>Germany?</hi> They complaine the Parliament and Aſſembly have done ſo little: Thanks to theſe <hi>Remoras?</hi> They ſhould doe leſſe if they could hinder them. Theſe vermine that ferr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t into by corners grawing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells of religion, and eating out the power thereof, firſt biting at Miniſtry, then at Magiſtracy theſe <hi>dungwagons</hi> make us ſtink in the noſtrills of all neighbouring Nations. But for ſooth their Judges are not infallible; Very true. If you aske ſeeing we may poſſibly erre, how can we be aſſured we doe not? I aske you againe ſeei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g, your eye ſight may deceive you how can you be ſure you ſee the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:162242:8"/> Sunne when you doe ſee it. Perhaps you may be in a dreame, and perhaps you and all the men in the World have been ſo, when they thought they were awake, and then only a wake, when they thought they dreamt. Becauſe we challenge not an impoſſibility of erring, can we not be ſure that all ought to be ſubject to the higher powers, (which you labour to kicke off) and that all ſowers of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and ſtrife and contentious perſons are in the wrong, not to ſay what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes that ſuch ſhall not enter into the Kingdome of God? Becauſe the Biſhops impoſed the <hi>nicknames</hi> of Puritan and Sectary, cannot we be ſure they are <hi>your true names,</hi> and pitty it is they ſhould be <hi>Chriſtian names?</hi> Doe you thinke there ever was any ſuch thing as Schiſme or faction? if ſo, give the Magiſtrate leave to find it out and puniſh it or elſe ſet up your ſtandard and own it. What pitty tis theſe men are not allowed to ride on a while! What a fine Egyptian miſcellany of religions would be introduced! We ſhould ſhortly have Mahomet <hi>the ſecond</hi> appeare with new revelations freſhly coined in the mint of ſome Ulcerous braines the itch of whoſe wit dayly breakes out into ſome new botch or boyle, <hi>for which they deſerve not little a clawing.</hi> Sure they have retrived St. <hi>Thomas</hi> his Goſpell out of the Vatican and would expound it in their Synagogues. <hi>Profecto ſi eſſent in republica magiſtratus nullum futurum fuiſſe Romae, (vel Londinis) niſi publicum conſilium: nunc in mille curias concioneſque cum alia in eſquiliis, alia in Aventino fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant conſilia diſperſam &amp; diſſipatem eſſe rempublicam?</hi> Under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a new miſtery crept in the Bachanalia to <hi>Rome</hi> a Seminary of the moſt horrid impieties, that ever were heard of yet veiled over with ſuch a faire ſhew of pure devotion that it was ſpread all over <hi>Italy</hi> before the Senate tooke notice thereof and then hardly with the death of many thouſands, and baniſhment of more, could ſtifle this Grecian Independency.</p>
            <p>Doe not many moderne Libertines tread the ſame path, rending man and wife, Father and Son a ſunder, breaking the neareſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ands, and captivating ſimple ſoules into their new miſteries which hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly three or foure of their whole tribe underſtand where for ought we know, they are innitiated into as arrant deeds of darkeneſſe as thoſe of the <hi>Bacchanalia?</hi> I am ſure theſe and the German Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtick conventicles run but too paralell. Neither will thoughts
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:162242:8"/> of charity here ſatisfie a Maſter of a family, who is knowingly to rende acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unt of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſe committed to his care. <hi>But thus moſt neceſſary truths may be ſuppreſſed.</hi> Thus thoſe errours which are neceſſary indeed for your building <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd without the rooting whereof, your <hi>Babell</hi> will tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uppreſſed together with their inſinuating Brokers, <hi>as upon the like</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>it hath been in all ages.</hi> I will brand them in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and leave them: They are Intruders into other mens labours, reaping where they have not ſowne, worthleſſe <hi>drones</hi> who can by no <hi>embleme</hi> be livelier repreſented, then <hi>of Ants,</hi> that rob others barnes to encreaſe their proper ſtore ſtealers of corne for their owne proviſions, induſtrious for themſelves to all others unprofitable: The true Paſtor is not ſo, but l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke a <hi>Bee</hi> innoxious, in-offenſive, without any's preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice gathers his hony for others, eating as pleaſant as profitable.</p>
            <p>Yet againe <hi>They are not ſatisfied that Controverſies in Religion can be truſted to the compulſive regulation of any.</hi> No, that's agreed upon you are pretty well reſolved againſt ſatisfaction. Muſt nothing then be done in a State, til <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mutineer be pleaſed to be ſatisfied, no law paſſe till every Cobl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r be fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt made to comprehend the reaſons which urg'd the enacting? what if his braines be too ſwimming, and will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of impreſſion? What if the Tinker tell us the Tavern is his <hi>meeting houſe,</hi> where he firſt drawes the barrell dry, then ſets himſelfe a broach, and inſpired by the ſpirit of wine, ſpits out his froth (miſcalled prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching) in the ſame veſſell? Truly ſirs, you muſt come off your ſtilts, and have this principle beat into you; That not the Magiſtrate ought to render yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reaſon, much leſſe Goſpell, for all his Ordinances; but unleſſe you can diſmount them with demonſtrative arguments, not ſimple cavillations, out of Gods word, Gods word commands you to ſubmit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note.</hi> Two ſorts of people offend in point of Religion, ſome have a depraved notion of God, and his worſhip, but confined to themſelves; and theſe deſerve a teacher, rather then a torturer, and to be dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in the ſpirit of meekneſſe. Others are not only <hi>Errones,</hi> but <hi>Turbones, ſtirrers as well as errors,</hi> and have ſuckt the ſame malice from their errors, as is ſaid to be concomitant of the plague, <hi>viz.</hi> an itch of ſpreading their Leproſie. Now if it be fellony to intrude into compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with a Plague ſore, what puniſhment deſerve theſe ſoule infecters? Since the Jewes for their malicious artifice in ſowing the Peſtilence,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:162242:9"/> were juſtly baniſhed many Countries, what ſhall be done to theſe, who by their Emiſſaries ſcatter their poyſon in all places? Either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine them to the Peſt-houſe, or let them not walke without a white wand ſome diſtinguiſhing marke whereby they may be knowne and ſhunned. 'Twas a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Heathens ſpeech, <hi>Sen. de Ben. l. 3. cap. 6. Violatarum religionum ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bi a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aliubi diverſa poena eſt, ſed ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aliqua;</hi> Better one periſh then unity. Can an injury be done to God, and not us? Therefore Clemency is here cruelty: for certainly if the lawes are binding only to morall duties, and looſe to Chriſtian, the Magiſtrate to us beares the Sword in vaine.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The Remonſtrative part winds up the ſixth grievance in theſe termes: <hi>The oppreſſive Monopoly of Merchant-Adventurers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe ſtill remaine, to the great abridgement of the Liberty of the People, and to the extreme prejudice of all ſuch induſtrious people, as doe depend on Clothing, or Woollen manufacture it being the ſtaple Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Kingdome, and to the great diſcouragement of all Tradeſmen, Seafaring-men, and hindrance of Shipping and Navigation.</hi> Grant all this to be true, yet you muſt give us leave to doubt of your honeſt meaning; for he that uſeth by-wayes, is juſtly miſtruſted when hee keepes the roade. The ingenuous are to be conſtrued by their natures, the crafty, by their ends: The plaine hearted ſeldome ſuppreſſe their inclinations: The cunning man lookes one way, rowes another, and while he holds up artificiall hands, with his naturall under his cloak, cuts your purſe. Here 'tis call'd a Monopoly, in the ſixth Article <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Company, ſo that when they cry downe this Company <hi>and others,</hi> till they explaine, we may feare they ſtrike obliquely at all the <hi>London</hi> Companies, at leaſt of Merchants. And indeed this is but conſonant to their doctrine, which urges an univerſall Community, and eſteemes every encloſure a Monopoly. But that, part hereof is falſe, and all the reſt miſtimed in the motion; The Weſterne Gentlemen will beare me witneſſe, who in the Houſe have no ſmall ſway, and will for their own Intereſt have a ſpeciall eye to Clothing, the chiefe riches of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, the Weſt being the ſtaple of this ſtaple commodity.</p>
            <p n="7">7 In the Preface I find theſe motives to your ſeventh Article. <hi>Alſo the old, tedious, and chargeable way of deciding ſuits in Law is continued to the undoing of multitudes of Families.</hi> The more undone, the better for you, for the pooreſt are apteſt to embrace your doctrine of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unity
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:162242:9"/> beſides, whence comes this care of us, ſince all out of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church are Heathens in your account? No wonder, if your <hi>new wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> love not to walke in any <hi>old way:</hi> But wiſer men then you, who ever you are, did not uſe in old wayes to ſtumble at every ſtone, nor to caſt off old cuſtomes, till old cuſtomes were ready to caſt off them, and if any law grew burdenſome, they let it fall through diſuſe, and antiquated rather then innovated; Phyſitians will tell you it is unſafe to diſturbe an evill ſetled humour, and when an infirmity hath kept poſſeſſion twenty, thirty, forty yeares, 'twere madneſſe to try experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon an aged body. Many Mountebanks, indeed by boaſting their new receipts, as you doe, often find ſome impatient foole or other. who had rather die quickly, then live in a little paine, and weighes not the hazard, in reſpect of the <hi>diſpatch.</hi> But we poore mortalls are content to thinke the old way the ſafeſt, till your new lights diſcover a better, for a Tinker will tell you, 'tis eaſier to find holes then mend them. Againe, you ſhoot beyond the Moone, when you ſtile this the <hi>moſt palpable and greateſt grievance in the world;</hi> For who ſo knowes any thing in Forraigne affaires, knowes there is never a Kingdome in the Chriſtian world, where the courſe of law is more regular leſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and conſequently leſſe chargeable, although indeed, their Fees be leſſer, then in <hi>England;</hi> Nay therefore is the Forraigne way more te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, becauſe leſſe chargeable, therefore in demanding a more <hi>ſpeedy, plaine, unburdenſome way of deciding controverſies, and the publication of our Lawes in Engliſh,</hi> you doe like the ſonnes of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> and aske you know not what. Sure I am in <hi>France</hi> and other parts, where the Fees are moderate, and the Lawes in their owne language, there are a hundred Families to our one, utterly ruined by ſuites which continue from Father to Sonne, even to the third and fourth generation, for where it coſts but twelve pence a time, every one will run to the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, and where every worm eaten canker'd fellow can have his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate for his halfe crowne, the leaſt Punctilio muſt bee pleaded, and the ſmalleſt difference turne to a Proceſſe. There is another reaſon of their miſchiefe: For where the Law is not lockt up, as it were in a ſtrange character, as with us, but the way eaſie, and the doore open for all commers; Every Peazants ſonne leaps to the Bar, till Lawyers ſwarme like Locuſts, as in <hi>France,</hi> whereas their principall ſtudy muſt be in each Village to ſow and foment diviſions, for feare of ſtarving?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:162242:10"/> Do not we frequently ſee fellows otherwiſe quarrelſome enough, &amp; mutually incenſed commit their differences to the arbitrement of neighbours meerly for feare of charges? And if yet ſome pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh people will never be well till they have paid for it, how out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious would they be when they might diſquiet others with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe detriment to themſelves? for my part I cannot but eſteeme it wiſely done of our State to fix ſome difficulties upon the ſtudy of the <hi>Common Law,</hi> which were they all removed we ſhould ſoon have all <hi>England</hi> full of brawles becauſe full of leaders even as now the facility of going to Law tempts many neare to <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> to their utter undoing who had they lived in <hi>Wales</hi> or <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> would never have dreamt thereof. Well but is this all? are they content to accuſe our Lawes of injuſtice: no they further re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uire <hi>that they be reduced to the neereſt agreement with chriſtianity &amp; that all proceſſe and proceedings theri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be true that ſo this nation may be freed of an oppreſſion more burdenſome and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome then all the oppreſſions hitherto by this Parliament remoued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How furiouſly th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe <hi>Jeh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s</hi> drive boaſting their zeal for the Lord pray God it end not as <hi>Iehu's</hi> in the accompliſhment of their own ends. In the interim we ſtand deeply charged: with Paganiſme, what no leſſe then unchriſtian? I confeſſe they are ancient yet can hardly believe K <hi>Alfred</hi> fetcht his Lawes from <hi>China</hi> or that our forefathers have ſinceborrowed any of the Turkiſh Aleoran or Jewiſh <hi>Talmud</hi> althoughall theſe have many excellent conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, As impertinent, is the other charge of untruth upon the proceedings which is an arrant falſhood. But give the childe his bable before he cry I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uppoſe now the Law's in Engliſh without any abbreviation, all fees limited and in print, will it therefore follow this nation ſhall be for ever free? you Platonicks may pleaſe your ſelves with your fine Idea's, but verily you ſeeme to underſt and the world as ittle as you underſtand your ſelves, and thoſe that know you ſay that's little enough, The regular uſuall fee of a Phyſician's but tenne ſhillings yet whether to engroſſe the Doctours care or out of oftentation. I know not by what meanes it's come about that between the Phyſician and Apothecary many are purged of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uities and are hardly left ſo much gold in their purſes, as there
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:162242:10"/> is about their pilles, whoſe fault is this now? muſt each mans fault be laid upon the States ſhoulders? ſo were the Councellours high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt legall fee, a piece, might not one all whoſe hopes lay at ſtake in one cauſe underhand quicken his diligence with ten The like a ſecond and a third in a like neceſſity, til the wheeles run in the old track? Nay may he not with more equity demand of me ten pounds, in ſome cauſe then one in another? ſhould the fees be preſcribed according to the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaders pains, or the cauſes impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? for may not a buſineſſe of mighty concernment be often diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht with leſſe trouble then a petty but knotty caſe caſe can be opened? as you may ſooner read two chapters in a fair legible character then one in a ſmall impreſſion. Again how can a Lawyers pains be eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated? either in the well timing a motion (for every buſineſſe hath its golden houre) or in the manner, or in the choice of the matter, or in the expedition, a hundred wayes order it how you can, an active faithfull mans pains are invaluable, and in many ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes cannot be weighed in other ballances then thoſe of diſcretion To conclude, you may as eaſily make a coat for the Moon as limit Lawyers ſees. Something perhaps might be amended, and will in time convenient, but to make ſuch a mountain of this mole hill, as in compariſon thereof to make nothing of the Starchamber, High Commiſſion, Court of Wards, and all other Court tyranny makes manifeſtro all who eye your practiſes that there lies a ſnake under this green graſſe; once I will be your <hi>Edipus</hi> and unfold this riddle. I find in my ſtory of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tzer</hi> that Arch-Anabaptiſt, among other his tenents <hi>That Iuſtice and Iudge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent under the new Teſtament ought to be framed and adminiſtred only out of the word of God</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y which do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine he made the poore People of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>huringia</hi> believe their Laws and Governments were unlawfull, and challenging to himſelfe by degrees the cognizance of all both Eccleſiaſticall and Civill mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Our Anabaptiſts are not yet grown big enough to ſpeak plain and therefore whiſper in their preachments <hi>that there are ſtronger truths to be revealed but we are not yet able to beare them.</hi> Firſt our Lawes muſt be disgraced and accounted as remote from Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, no doubt becauſe they are not all drawn out of the Goſpell. Next our Parliament muſt be beſpattered becauſe they will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them to their minds: then will ſome contrary <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb facs="tcp:162242:11"/> himſelf to the people, by condemning our Statutes for tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and extracting a quite-eſſentiall Law out of his chimericall revelations, which his Sectaries ſhall cry up for Goſpell. Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reads me, read but the lives of theſe Plebicolae, and after a moneth or two's obſervation you ſhall find them ſinging <hi>Abſalons</hi> tune in every corner to the people; <hi>Your matters are good and right but there is no man deputed to heare you O that our Goſpell might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nco prevail in the land, that every man that every man that hath any ſuit or cauſe might come unto us and we would do them iuſtice.</hi> The whole bent of their wit all their turnings, and windings and fetches; tend but to this to poſſeſſe the people againſt the preſent Government for this they affirme as many divers ſhapes as <hi>Proteus,</hi> with the honeſt minded inſinuating a certain miſterious ſtrictneſſe of converſation with the ambitious, they deale by communications of honours, telling them what a ſweet thing it is to be lookt upon as chief of a party, that its better being the head of a Cat then the taile of a Lion; But deale how you can with them they will amuſe and hold you in ſuſpence, but you ſhall never ſqueeſe out of them what they would have, nor indeed can they tell you being reſolved to ſet up more or leſſe ſayle according as the wind ſhall blow. Marke this phraſe in concluſion. <hi>To the neareſt agreement with Chriſtianity</hi> as if Politicall Lawes could not quite agree therewith, or we be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then mungrell Chriſtians while we retained any. This is pure Liberty.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>That the life of no perſon may be taken away under the teſtimonie of two witneſſe to doe it upon the teſtimony of one you ſay is contrary to the law of God or common equity.</hi> This is a grievance you have learn't by revelation, for I find no ſuch thing in our lawes: Indeed in ſome caſes of main importance for the example, where many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances compoſe a chaine of ſtrong probabilities concurring with the depoſition of a diſintereſſed eye witneſſe I ſay in ſome ſuch rare caſe the law allowes puniſhment of a notorious offender; And what can you picke out of this b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne now? But you muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded for the ſole deliverers from all bondage? <hi>And that in an equitable way you will proportion puniſhment to offences ſo that no mans life be taken away his body puniſhed nor his eſtate forfeited but upon ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eighty and conſiderable cauſes as juſtly deſerve ſuch pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments.</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:162242:11"/> What your Synagogues account juſt we neither know nor care, but there is no man puniſhed by the lawes in any of theſe reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects without ſuch cauſe as the whole Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> for many, many hundred yeares ſucceſſively have deemed weighty <hi>And that all priſoners may have a ſpeedy tryall?</hi> Amen ſo be it, and may yours lead the dance; <hi>that they be neither ſtarved, nor their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies ruined by long and lingring impriſonment. And that impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be only uſed for ſafe euſtody not puniſhment.</hi> To a Gentleman complaining of the dearnes of Sacke, his companion merrily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, If it were at a crowne the quart we ſhould have fewer drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards: So ſay I, if perſons were yet more troubleſome perſons would be more orderly; you ſee as bad as they are, there are ſtill enough found, that by their folly or obſtinacy will venter the going thither. But now what if there ariſe crimes of contumacie, obſtinate opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>neſſe, ſedition, pertinacity in ſpeaking evill of dignities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By the practiſe of all the Common-wealths that ever I read or heard of, Impriſonment hath been judged the moſt expedient puniſhment. 1. Becauſe theſe crimes are of a diffuſſive nature and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement the moſt proper remedy. 2. That ſolitarineſſe might breed in their minds, reflex thoughts and ſo occaſion repentance. 3. The indulgence of the magiſtrate could pitch upon no milder way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he ſhould proclaime impunity for all crime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not capitall; This being the ordinary gradation of ſuch, that the firſt fault draws on Impriſonment, and ſometimes fine, continuation in it Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſurreptuious return from exile, or a third guilt of the ſame crime death, What intereſt you have in deprecating ſuch penall proceedings, Let your own Conſciences determine.</p>
            <p>Another fooles bolt is ſhot againſt <hi>tythes &amp; al other inforced main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and that nothing in place therof be impoſed but that all Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters may be payd only by thoſe who voluntarily chuſe them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trace with them for their Labours.</hi> That is being interpreted, that excepting <hi>London</hi> and the adjacent Counties, all Miniſters ſhould be expeld the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> and how many thinke you would be left in the Dominion of <hi>VVales?</hi> Truly conſidering the pretty ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> age we live in; I wonder no ſuch whimſycall Petition as this was ever tendred, Humbly ſhewiug &amp;c. That whereas for divers yeares paſt there have beene ſundry differences happened in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion to the detriment of the publike peace, They would
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:162242:12"/> be pleaſed to order a ſuſpenſion of all the Miniſtry for 12. months, till all contentions about Gods worſhip ceaſe. How thinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou? would not hands enough be got thereto? I, and ſeales too: With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a while people would be ſo far from diſputing of God. that they would never thinke of him, your Petition hath the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſence. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der other tearmes. The old Proverbe was Lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prieſt, like People and both were bad enough; But if it be inverted, Like People, Like Prieſt, we ſhall ſee famous <hi>contracts,</hi> and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>worthy labours</hi> all performed in a blind alehouſe. If tythes came ſo hardly. when ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted from them by authority, is it to be imagined, their contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions will flow in more liber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly? The naked truth is this; If theſe ſhockes were out of the way <hi>Iohn</hi> or <hi>Leydens</hi> Prophets might happily reap the better harveſt; for its probable they would plant their Goſpell, with equall zeale to the Spaniards in the Indies. We are told there is no ground <hi>for either under the Goſpell.</hi> A ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cavill: The whole Orthodox Church of God for theſe foureteen or fifteene hundred yeares, that is ever ſince any Churches were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, have acknowledged more then abundant ground for both; Now becauſe theſe fanatick dreamers find it not couched in ſo many Letters and Sylables, they moſt ſimply yet moſt wickediy cry downe all legall maintenance and upon the ſame ground all our other lawes: For tythes or any other maintenance were never ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by us as a precept of the Goſpell, but as the law of <hi>England,</hi> and therfore in the ſeventh Petition they in effect demand the abrogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of al our laws becauſe not expreſly contained in the Goſpel there tearmed <hi>Chriſtianity:</hi> Yet I need not grant them thus much for all ſound Chriſtians acknowledging a perfect harmony in the word, that the old Teſtament is but <hi>Chriſt under the veile,</hi> and the new <hi>Moſes unveiled</hi> its enough for us to practiſe what God thought fit to be injoyned in the one, till we find it poſitively, or by ſtrong inference (for we will not tye them ſo ſtrictly to it as they doe us) retracted in the other. But this is another dreame of theſe Pſeudo-Evangeliſts to oppoſe <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt, contending that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of faith delivered in the old and new Teſtament is divers in ſubſtance and that Chriſt in the new Teſtament propoſed quite a new doctrine. Thoſe that will be blind, Let them be blind ſtill; But God forbid the whole Kingdom ſhould therefore put out their eyes.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:162242:12"/>10. <hi>That you will take ſome ſpeedy and effectuall courſe to relieve all ſuch priſoners for debt as are altogether unable to pay, that they may not periſh in priſon, through the hard heartedneſſe of their Creditors,</hi> that the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion may go down the better, they annex this clauſe as a gobbet of ſugar <hi>and that all ſuch who have eſtates may be enforced to make payment and not ſhelter themſelves in Priſon to defraud their Creditors.</hi> This was wiſely moved believe me; could you but ſet the do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res open and proclaim Jubile to all priſoners you might happily gain no ſmall ſtore of Proſelytes, your communion of goods would take fire here like Gunpowder; how quickly would ſuch as have nothing left, cry halves with their neighbours, ? but by your leave, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> motion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad been juſter that <hi>ſome ſtricter puniſhment beſides priſon may be inflicted upon all ſuch deſperate ſpendthrifts as will rather obſtinately hazard the periſhing in priſon through their hard heartedneſſe to their Creditou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s then bate an ace of their vain expences wherewithall to diſcharge the debt.</hi> Sure while the worſt of it is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat to priſon' where many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive jollily and in riot they beare up as long as they may and then let poſterity ſink or ſwim. Now admit the worſt what proportion is there between the ruine of one man who hath ſpent his dayes in vanity and folly and the whole families deſolation? They erre who think puniſhments invented onely for the offenders; they are for example ſake and to deter others. Are not many for crimes, which by reaſon of age or other impediments they are no more able to commit yet hang'd up for <hi>ſcarre-Growes?</hi> It's a moſt unjuſt cuſtome of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> when any man is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacht for murder, the people uſually help him to eſcape with this <hi>booriſh</hi> argument one man is killed already, why ſhould we loſe another? moſt fooliſh pity, yea moſt wicked! I my ſelf have known a dozen murthers in one yeare by this meanes eſcape unpuniſhed, all which might poſſibly have been prevented, had the firſt mvrthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer been hanged. Thoſe who pity not themſelves who can pity? and in caſe of ſuretiſhip the uſuall weakneſſe of ſoft natures, or whatſoever elſe may merit regulation, we leave it to thoſe whom it concerns without impoſing our ſence upon the <hi>ſupreme Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[11 In the next place here is a great ſtir about Priſon keepers, &amp; their under Officers, I will joyne with you herein, and wiſh they may be of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:162242:13"/> approved honeſty, but rather wiſh it, then hope it, for I know not by what fare, they have never been better then they are; The contagion of the place, I thinke, infects them. But that you ſhould now foiſt this in, to make up your Bakers dozen of grievances, is moſt, moſt ridiculous! What a happy condition were we in, if we lay under no greater bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den then this of Knaviſh Priſon-Keepers. It's a ſigne you have little to ſay, when you interrupt the State-proceedings with ſuch petty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: Is not this a worthy buſineſſe, thinke you, for the Parliaments cognizance, in the midſt of the greateſt difficulties, that ever Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment groaned under? This is with <hi>Rachel</hi> to ſay, Give me children or elſe I dye: Is the Parliament in ſtead of God? Sometime you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile them, here you deifie them. Can they make men honeſt? they may indeed diſplace knaves, but to hinder others from becomming as bad, is not their worke but Gods; Muſt the State be troubled with the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and diſplacing every under Officer? There is one miſterious phraſe lurkes here, <hi>That they may detaine no perſon or perſons without lawfull warrant.</hi> Doe they otherwiſe? why doe not thoſe detained exhibit their complaints? for this is abſolutely illegall, and the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper would be ſoundly fined in any Court of <hi>England:</hi> So that 'tis frivolous here to trouble the ſupreme Court. Stay a little, for I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, I can't pick ſence enough out of this to fill a nut-ſhell, except you meane a Parliament Warrant is unlawfull; for who elſe hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any? 'Tis even ſo, The Houſe of Peers, or a Committee of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, hath ſent ſome of your Knipperdollings to priſon for their rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and this makes you plead ſo hard for priſoners; All the reſt of the Article was but a ſhooing-horne to draw on this clauſe. But I would wiſh you to be more modeſt, and not to harp too much upon this ſtring. for vetily, <hi>if you ſcratch your Superiours too hard, you may chance draw the ſmart upon your ſelves. Qui nimis emangit, ſanguinem elieit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>That you will provide ſome powerfull meanes to keep men, women and children from begging, and wickedneſſe, that this Nation may be no longer a ſhame to Chriſtianity therein.</hi> I am confident no Nation under heaven hath better provided for the poore by lawes, then ours, nor any where, <hi>Holland</hi> excepted, are they better executed: name me any King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in Chriſtendome where are fewer poore? beſides that, many who ſeeme poore among us are but counterfeit, and beg out of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:162242:13"/> out of a vagrant humour of Libertiniſme, which me thinkes, you of all others ſhould not gain-ſay. Nevertheleſſe I deny not but they might be better ordered, and would be in that Government which you ſo much withſtand. It cannot be unknowne to you alſo, how the City for their parts, have been of late conſulting hereabout; ſo that it ill becomes you <hi>Plebicola,</hi> to act the <hi>Publicola,</hi> and to commend your ſelves to the people for the firſt movers of that, which hath been above theſe twelve moneths, to my knowledge, <hi>in ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tation,</hi> and that's a point beyond <hi>motion.</hi> But ſuch is your arrogance, as that you would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre to the people, that no body ſees their grievances, but you, all the reſt of the world is blind, <hi>and hardly can you afford the Parliament one oye as the Chineſi doe</hi> the Europeans. And whence (I pray) this ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der regard of the poore? doe not we know that we are all Infidels in your eſteeme? What care you for all the poore in the world, that are out of your congregations? Verily of all graces, you have leaſt cauſe to brag of charity. Well, I ſay no more, but wiſh your heart may here have kept your tongue company; So ſhall I hope, you may in time come to be <hi>honeſt Elders,</hi> ſince you are already ſo <hi>ſtont Deacons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 The laſt is a Voluminous complaint, 1. <hi>That men call them by their names, of Sectaries, Schiſmaticks, factious, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis well they are aſhamed of the name, 'twere better they were aſhamed of the thing; they diſavow the titles, but not the tenents. Their argument runnes thus; All honeſt people, and ſuch as would not conforme to the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions under Epiſcopacy, the then preſent Government, were formerly moſt unjuſtly reproached as Puritans, Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither are we truly ſo called for reſiſting the preſent Government, <hi>(Although all thoſe ſtumbling blocks be now removed, and ſo the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why you refuſe to joyne with us yet inviſible.)</hi> I will match their Argument, and then turne them both looſe to ſtand or fall together. In the raigne of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> divers Socinians ſuppreſſing their blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous tenents, and only preaching againſt adoration of Images, Purgatory, Invocation of Saints, and other popiſh ſuperſtitions, are therefore taken for Proteſtants, and together with the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants perſecuted as Hereticks for oppoſing Papiſticall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Afterward in the beginning of Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> raigne while the reformed diſcipline of the Church was yet unſetled, they begin to peep as from under the maske, and by degrees to appeare in their own like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:162242:14"/> ſeducing many ſimple people, who had admired them for their zeale gainſt the Papiſts. Now if theſe men apprehended for their horrid blaſphemies againſt the Trinity, and other fundamentall Articles of our Creed, ſhould come and plead not guilty, becauſe the beſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s had beene branded with the name of Hereticks, as well as they, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that they were Scmſmaticks, although they rent the Church, and obſtructed the reformation becauſe the moſt godly had likwiſe refuſed to common cate with the Papiſts, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uppoſe you would thinke this infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence more worthy of laughter then an anſwer. We doe not ſay ſome of you are Hereticks, and others of you are Schiſmaticks, becauſe ſo called; but we call you ſo, becauſe you are ſo: Neither doe we terme you factious and ſeditions; only becauſe you refuſe to conforme to the preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> government, but for that you therefore refuſe it, becauſe injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d by the Magiſtrate, out of a pure ſpirit of contradiction whereby you ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke the foundations of all Authority. And therefore to your ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d branch of this Article, <hi>That you will not exclude any of approved f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>lity from bearing office of truſt in the Common-wealth for nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</hi> I retorne this anſwer: If any remain unſatisfied in any point of the preſent government, and be ready modeſtly to render a reaſon of his non conformity, no doubt he ſhall be borne withall, and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded therefore from any office of truſt; for ſuch a one will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to keep his opinions to himſelfe. But we know that moſt of you value not that tolleration which allowes not the ſpreading of your Hereſies, wherefore we have as little reaſon to truſt you, as the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in the former caſe to have truſted the Socinians, who might have pleaded as much fervour againſt the Papiſts, as you can againſt the Royalliſts. What are we the better for your milke, if now you kicke downe the paile? If you are good, and doe good, ſhall you not be accepted? and if you doe not good, ſin lies at the doore, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under the threſhold. You ſay you are the Parliaments <hi>reall friends,</hi> but I am ſure you ſhew little reſpect, and leſſe friendſhip, when you tell them (to their face? Nay, to the face of the whole world) that <hi>their Promotion of Malignants is the chiefe cauſe of all our grievances.</hi> Laſtly, that you may end like your ſelves, <hi>you tell the Parliament, they are going to leave this Nation in great thraldoms both of body, mind, and eſtate</hi> (is uot this to hunt counter to the title of right Honourable in the beginning?) the ſole prevention whereof conſiſts in the granting
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:162242:14"/> your <hi>humble deſire, without which this Nation cannot be ſafe and happy</hi> This is a very humble concluſion indeed! but ſomething unlike a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to ſay you muſt have what you aske, and cannot bee without it. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ggars had not wont to be chuſers till of late, can you tell be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t what's <hi>proper for the Parliament to gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> then they themſelves? you pretend I con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe, <hi>the generall good of the Common-wealth,</hi> but it your lives and converſations you walke more like our Antipodes then our Country-men.</p>
            <p>But I am weary of raking in this dunghill. He that would know what we may juſtly feare from this Gallimaufrey of E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> let him <hi>reade Spanhemins</hi> Hiſtoricall natration of the German Sect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, where in the beginning of the ſecond Chapter, you ſhall meet with a diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our preſent calamities: Thoſe that are unacquainted with Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory are apt to thinke all Relations of ſuch proceedings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>abulous, ſo ridiculous and ſantaſtick are many of their principles. But ſo much the more daugerous are the effects, becauſe we are ſo prune to ſlight the cauſes. Marke but the progreſſe of Herefie in all ages, and you will eaſily diſcover whether we are going: <hi>for that which hath been, ſhall bee, and there is no new thing under the Sun.</hi> The pretences have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alwayes been the ſame, of ſweet communion, and encreaſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the progreſſe the ſame, the caſting of the Ordinances of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie, and Miniſtery, the event the ſame, the trouble of the Church for a while, but ever in the end their owne confuſion. The ſtorme of Perſecution was no ſooner blowne over in the Primitive times, then thoſe civill warres of Religion began to divide the Church, and ſo from time to time interchangeably continued till all ſetled in a groſſe fog of ignorance under Popery: Againe, God no ſooner ſtirred up <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and his fellowes to reforme, then the Divell transforming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into an angell of light, ſtirted up the Anabaptiſts to retard and corrupe the reformation. And how? by exclaiming againſt it as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, condemning <hi>Luther</hi> for a flatterer of Princes, as if he had left the people under tyranny, and had not preached the full liberty of the Goſpell; by which doctrine and cruell indulgence of the Migiſtrate in a ſhort ſpace they drew after them whole armies of licentious people, and lead them againſt their Princes. Which example puts me in mind of <hi>Appius,</hi> ſaying in <hi>Livi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Non miſerris, ſed l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eentia tantum concitum
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:162242:15"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t laſciv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re magis pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bem quam ſavire.</hi> All the ſury is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the heads of theſe factions, the reſt are mad by contagion. To wind up all in a Character of our Petitioners: 1. The whole rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of them, is a beggars cloak made up of divers patches. A faire well built body to the eye but uncaſe it, and you find an ill ſhapen car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſe covered over with a thick cruſt of appearances. 2. Their voice is <hi>Iacobs,</hi> but their hands are <hi>Eſan's.</hi> 3. Their defigne is to clog the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament with endleſſe intricacy of worke, that they may ſcape in the crowd unſeene, till the Monſter be full growne, and then locke it in the face who dare. Every good Patriot weigh well, and conſider their actions! Trace them afar off, but tread not in their footſteps: Harken rather to <hi>Salomon. Prov. 22. v, 8. Pro. 24. v. 21. Remove not the ancient land-markes which thy Fathers have ſet, and againe. My ſon feare thou the Lord, and the King: and meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi> If God challenge the firſtlings, give the Magiſtrate the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond fruits of thine Obedience.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
